Soviet Union Mennonite Subject Files, Inclusive: 1963-2001, undated, Bulk: 1974-1988.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Mennonite Subject Files
Inclusive: 1963-2001, undated, Bulk: 1974-1988.
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
46
Keston Institute, 1969 -
22 folders
The Soviet Union Mennonite Files contain a variety of materials about the history, lives, movement, and discrimination in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
The Keston Center received materials regarding Mennonites in the Soviet Union from 1963 through 2001. The majority of the content relates to the history of Mennonites and their communities in the Soviet Union and Russia, as well as Soviet Mennonite emigrants.
Mennonites appear to have first migrated to Russia in the late 1700s and early 1800s in search of a home where they would not be required to serve in the military because of their pacifist beliefs. By the Franco-Prussian War in the 1870s, Russia mandated military enlistment, and many Mennonites fled the country. A large group emigrated to Canada, with a few to the northern United States. Many who remained in the Soviet Union and lived through World War II, temporarily fled to Germany but were ultimately forced to return to the USSR. Therefore, families were split apart for decades. Because of the large number of separated families, there were organizations during the 1970s whose purpose was to gain permission for Mennonites to leave the USSR and reunite with family members living in Canada.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Mennonite Files contain newspapers, newspaper clippings, articles, abstracts, newsletters, handwritten notes, and bibliographies. These documents span from 1963-2001 with primary focus from 1974-1988.
The majority of the content address the history of Mennonites in the Soviet Union, as well as their emigration from the USSR. Many documents detail the lives of families who were separated following World War II and the process that brought them back together. Finally, there is information about those who immigrated to Canada from the Soviet Union at various points in time. Some key terms include Baptists, Registration, Mennonite Brethren, Church Mennonites, Canada, freedom, pacifism, reunification, British Columbia, Omsk, Estonia, and MCC (Mennonite Central Committee).
Arrangement
The Keston Center received the Mennonite documents organized by topic. The original filing system has been preserved, with documents in each folder organized by date. However, some documents were relocated based on labeling.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 46.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Keston College -- Archives.; Keston Institute -- Archives.; Mennonite Brethren Church
Places
Soviet Union -- Emigration and immigration.
Subjects
Family reunification.; Mennonites -- Canada.; Mennonites -- Soviet Union -- History.; Mennonites -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Abstracts.; Articles.; Bibliographies.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Newsletters.; Newspapers.
- General, 1963-2001, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series includes information about the history of the Mennonite Church in the Soviet Union and its members who emigrated to Canada.
  Acquisition Information
  Accession No. 46.
  - Mennonite Church. General (1 of 5), 1965-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mennonite Church. General (2 of 5), 1972 July, 1973 June and December, 1974 January-April (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mennonite Church. General (3 of 5), 1974 May-December, 1976 September, 1979 August, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mennonite Church. General (4 of 5), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mennonite Church. General (5 of 5), 1980 September, 1981 September, 1982 January-March, 1986 February, 1988 May, 1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - History of Mennonite Church in Soviet Union (1 of 2), 1973, 1974 January-May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - History of Mennonite Church in Soviet Union (2 of 2), 1974 June-December, 1975 April-October, 1976 January-August, 1978 April, 1985, 2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - History of Mennonite Church in Soviet Union. Soviet Period, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mennonite Individuals. Dotsenko, Boris, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mennonite Church Administration. Individual Churches, 1976 July, 1985 October (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mennonite Church-State Relations, 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Opening of New Mennonite Churches, 1979 June, 1981 January, 1985 October (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mennonite Church. Commendation in Secular Press, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mennonite Church Life, 1973, 1987 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mennonite Church Life. Parish Life, 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mennonite Church Life. Defection from Faith, 1986 September (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mennonite Church. International Relations. Western Reactions — Appeals, 1983 May (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mennonite Church. International Relations. Visits from Foreign Delegation, 1979 May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mennonite Church. Defection — Emigration on Religious Grounds (Germans), 1963 May, 1973 November, 1974 January-October, 1975 March-December, 1976 March, 1979 February, 1988 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mennonite Church. Schism — Doctrinal Differences, 1977 March (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mennonite Church. Relations with Fellow Believers, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Mennonite Church. Children and Youth, 1979 February (Box 1, Folder 22)